<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Berkeley Hills Explorer</string>

    <string name="paths_site_name_one">Rose Walk</string>
    <string name="paths_site_description_one">This historic and lovely path was designed in 1913 by Bernard Maybeck. After many of the homes were lost in the 1923 Berkeley fire, owners Frank and Florence Dickens Gray hired architect Henry Gutterson to design small homes on the northside of the path. Gutterson consulted with Bernard Maybeck to create homes that fully take advantage of the space. The homes on the south side were built in 1928, and the final house, built at the top of the stairs, was completed in 1936.</string>
    <string name="paths_site_name_two">Easter Way</string>
    <string name="paths_site_description_two">This lovely path, which stretches from Spruce to Cragmont Rock Park, was so named because of the Berkeley residents who would climb the path each year for an Easter morning service at Cragmont Rock Park.</string>
    <string name="paths_site_name_three">Tamalpais Path</string>
    <string name="paths_site_description_three">This majestic and magical wooded staircase climbs 183 steps through the trees. A hidden path past a gate leads you to a charming waterfall section of Codornices Creek.</string>
    <string name="paths_site_name_four">Vine Lane</string>
    <string name="paths_site_description_four">Note the unique ironwork sign marking this charming path, and the homes along the path, whose owners must walk the path daily to get to the street.</string>


    <string name="parks_site_name_one">Indian Rock Park</string>
    <string name="parks_site_description_one">Acreage: 1.18 acres — 51,400 sq. ft. \n
        \nHISTORY\n
        \nIndian Rock Park was a gift to the City of Berkeley from Mason-McDuffie Real Estate Company during its development of the Northbrae area. It was dedicated for park purposes in 1917. Dick Leonard, the “father of modern rock climbing,” and noted environmentalist David Brower, founder of Friends of the Earth, learned rock climbing and developed their mountaineering techniques at Indian Rock (and also at Cragmont Rock Park). Brower used this special knowledge to prepare training manuals during World War II, which proved critical in enabling the 86th Regiment of the U.S. Army to surprise the Germans at Riva Ridge in the North Apennines in Italy, the major action disrupting German lines in Southern Europe.\n
        \nTIPS\n
        \nThe path to the right has access to steps leading to the top. Be cautious about steep drop-offs on the other side while you are admiring the panoramic view. There is a possible lunch site across the street, but there are no toilets here. As a side trip, note the house built over a rock on Shattuck and the one next to it with a big oak growing on top of a large rock.\n
        \n
        \nDescription is courtesy of the Berkeley Path Wanderers Association.</string>
    <string name="parks_site_name_two">Great Stoneface Park</string>
    <string name="parks_site_description_two">Acreage: .73 acre  — 31,800 sq. ft. \n
        \nHISTORY\n
        \nGreat Stoneface Park was a gift to the City of Berkeley from the Mason-McDuffie Real Estate Company during its development of the Northbrae area. It was dedicated for park purposes in 1921. The feature that gave the park its name is now hard to see due to the shrubbery.\n
        \nGEOLOGY\n
        \nSome geologists believe that the rocks in this park are about 11-12 million years old. They are rhyolite, a volcanic rock. The rock could have been autobrecciated, meaning that that the lava rapidly congealed and became too viscous to flow and thus broke up explosively into pieces or ashes. Fault movements and landslides have greatly altered and moved the rocks over millions of years. Professor Lawson, who mapped the San Andreas and Hayward faults, named them Northbrae rhyolite in honor of this neighborhood. Apparently they were formed by volcanic activity in an area near Hollister, south of San Jose, so they have moved a long way. The rock is harder and different from other area volcanic rock, such as that found at Sibley Round Top.\n
        \n
        \nDescription is courtesy of the Berkeley Path Wanderers Association.</string>
    <string name="parks_site_name_three">Remillard Park</string>
    <string name="parks_site_description_three">Acreage 5.9 acres — 257,000 sq. ft. \n
        \nHISTORY\n
        \nThe property with Pinnacle Rock on it was donated to the City of Berkeley by Lillian Remillard Dandini in 1963. The City purchased additional acreage in 1969–1970. The interim landscape design, based on community input, was adopted in May 1969. In June 1969, $35,000 was allocated from Capital Improvement Program funds to develop a “rural park.” Informally known as Pinnacle Park, the Parks and Recreation Commission approved the dedication of Remillard Park, in memory of Lillian Dandini’s father, on October 22, 1964. The playground was constructed by community volunteers at a work party held on August 24, 1974 and redone more recently. The park was awarded the 1975 Park Facility Citation by the California Park and Recreation Society District III for neighborhood participation in design concepts and volunteer labor.\n
        \nDescription is courtesy of the Berkeley Path Wanderers Association.</string>
    <string name="parks_site_name_four">Cragmont Rock Park</string>
    <string name="parks_site_description_four">Acreage: 3 acres — 130,680 sq. ft. \n
        \nHISTORY\n
        \nNeighborhood residents bought the land for Cragmont Rock Park from the Cragmont Land Company and donated it to the City of Berkeley at purchase price. It was dedicated for park purposes in 1920. Dick Leonard, the “father of technical climbing,” formed the Cragmont Climbing Club, which was absorbed a few months later into the Sierra Club’s Rock Climbing Section. Using the techniques he had learned climbing at Cragmont Rock, Leonard planned the first technical rock climb in Yosemite in 1934. Leonard led over a hundred expeditions and climbs in the Sierra Nevada, at times with his friend, environmentalist David Brower, making many first ascents on mountains earlier thought impossible to climb.\n
        \nTIPS\n
        \nNote also the Mediterranean-style “village” across the street.
        \nToilets available. \n
        \nDescription is courtesy of the Berkeley Path Wanderers Association.</string>
    <string name="parks_site_name_five">Grotto Rock Park</string>
    <string name="parks_site_description_five">Acreage: .31 acre — 13,500 sq. ft. \n
        \nHISTORY\n
        \nGrotto Rock Park was a gift to the City of Berkeley from Mason-McDuffie Real Estate Company during its development of the Northbrae area. It was dedicated for park purposes in 1917.\n
        \nTIPS\n
        \nSteps from the right side do not go all the way to the top, but it is worth walking around to see the interesting shape of it all.\n
        \n
        \nDescription is courtesy of the Berkeley Path Wanderers Association.</string>
    <string name="parks_site_name_six">Mortar Rock Park</string>
    <string name="parks_site_description_six">Acreage: .39 acre — 16,990 sq. ft. \n
        \nHISTORY\n
        \nMortar Rock Park was yet another gift to the City of Berkeley from Mason-McDuffie Real Estate Company during its development of the Northbrae area. It was dedicated for park purposes in 1917.\n
        \nTIPS\n
        \nThere are steps around the right side, but it is not recommended to climb, as the view is mostly blocked and there isn’t much space at the top. It is nice to take the path through the rocks and along the side to see the mortar holes and also note the native trees. Acorns were ground here, with other items, and tannins perhaps leached out in nearby creeks.\n
        \n
        \nDescription is courtesy of the Berkeley Path Wanderers Association.</string>
    <string name="parks_site_name_seven">Contra Costa Rock Park</string>
    <string name="parks_site_description_seven">Acreage: .17 acre  — 7,410 sq. ft. \n
        \nHISTORY\n
        \nContra Costa Rock Park was also a gift to the City of Berkeley from Mason-McDuffie Real Estate Company during its development of the Northbrae area. It was dedicated for park purposes in 1917.\n
        \nTIPS\n
        \nTake the steps up from the left side, and exit via the back. Note the small caves on the return path on the south side.\n
        \n
        \nDescription is courtesy of the Berkeley Path Wanderers Association.</string>

    <string name="hikes_site_name_one">Easter Way to Cragmont Rock Park</string>
    <string name="hikes_site_description_one">2.2 miles long, nearly 700 ft. elevation gain \n
        \nWhile only 2.2 miles long, you\'re sure to get your heart rate up ambling around this network of meandering paths in the Berkeley Hills while enjoying marvelous views and eclectic architecture. \n
        \nTo access this hike by car, take the Albany exit on I-80, go up Marin Ave, then right on Los Angeles, followed by a left on Spruce. Park where you can on the 1000 block. Or use AC Transit route 67, which goes up Spruce from downtown Berkeley. \n
        \nHead up Spruce, crossing Santa Barbara Road (our return route) until you encounter our first set of steps, Easter Way. This path spans three blocks, and gives us a good start on our nearly 700 feet of elevation gain. The entrance to the third leg of Easter is 100 feet up Euclid and brings us to Cragmont Park. Take a moment to walk over to its viewing platform for a magnificent vista of the San Francisco Bay and Golden Gate. \n
        \nContinuing on Regal Road our next path (on the left) is Pinnacle, which takes up to Poppy Lane and Remillard Park, noted for its rather large rock (great for budding rock climbers). At the end of Poppy Lane we\'ll continue up Poppy Path to Miller Avenue. At this point, you\'ll probably have a growing appreciation for the hidden gardens and the many interesting building styles you\'ve encountered on the way. It only gets better. \n
        \nProceed to the right on Miller for about 1000 feet and hang a left for our last path up, Bret Harte Lane. At the crest, you\'ll find busy Grizzly Peak Boulevard (and an AC bus stop, the 65 Euclid). We\'ll head right and start our descent, turning onto Stevenson, where we\'ll pick up the Anne Brower Path. At the base (Miller Ave) briefly go left, then right down Whitaker Avenue passing Grizzly Peak Park and going right at the T intersection with Sterling, followed by an immediate left down on the Whitaker Path. \n
        \nAt Keeler Avenue go right, then left on the Upper Covert Path, cross Cragmont Avenue and continue on the lower section as it winds down through a gully to Keith Avenue. As you swing around to right on Keith, ignore the temptation to go down Redwood Terrace and go six houses more to the last path (of this hike) El Mirador, where you may encounter offerings left on the steps by previous visitors (or perhaps local gnomes). To get back to the start point go right on Euclid, then left on Cragmont and finally a left on Santa Barbara. As you may see from the maps, there are many other paths nearby that can extend this hike in a number of directions–for example you can continue up at Grizzly Peak Boulevard to Crescent Park and beyond to Tilden Park and Lake Anza. \n
        \nHike description is courtesy of Chas Blackford.\n
    </string>
    <string name="hikes_site_name_two">Park Hills Walk</string>
    <string name="hikes_site_description_two">
        \nDIRECTIONS\n
        \nBegin at Park Gate and Shasta Road. Follow Park Hills Road to Muir Way. Descend steps to the east, which lead to an interior park. Proceed north and east to Woodside Road. Head north on Woodside Road to The Crescent. Explore the interior park between The Crescent and Park Hills Road. Head south on Woodside Road to Hillview Road. Head south on Hillview Road to Fred Herbert Path. Follow the Fred Herbert Path steps back uphill to the starting point at Park Gate. \n
        \nBACKGROUND\n
        \nIn 1938 the Mason-McDuffie company purchased around 70 acres of land from the East Bay Regional Park District (or the predecessor water company). This area was named Park Hills and was intended to be for higher quality single family homes. Prototypes were provided by predecessor Mason-McDuffie developments in Claremont and Northbrae. Deed restrictions were placed upon lots sold. To assure continuity a nonprofit property owners association was formed; control was to passed to owners when half of the lots were sold. The association continues to this day. Roads were laid out in 1939. Development began in 1940. Planning was by the Olmsted Brothers of Brookline, MA. Four acres of wildflowers were provided by Professor Shepherd. Native plants for landscaping were provided by James Roof of the Tilden Botanic Garden. William Wurster designed the beautiful gate and fountain at Shasta Road. There were some signature pathways---see Fred Herbert which descends in sections from this point to Wildcat Canyon Road. Some blocks contained large neighborhood playgrounds at their center. In early 1942 there were 167 lots in the tract, 18 occupied homes and 3 unoccupied homes. \n
        \nBy the 1950\'s problems began to arise. This area was greatly isolated from the county seat in Martinez. Police and fire services were inadequate. Berkeley residents were getting better services for lower taxes. Enrolling children in the Orinda School District was impractical. In February 1957, 200 people from the property owners association attended the annual meeting at the Brazilian Room in Tilden Park. A committee of five was appointed to investigate the possibility of moving the Park Hills parcel from Contra Costa County to Alameda County. By July 1957, a bill making such a move possible had passed both the Assembly and Senate and had been signed by the Governor. In December 1958, an election was held for Park Hills and Berkeley Woods homeowners concerning annexation of these areas by the City of Berkeley; both areas elected to be annexed by wide margins. On February 1, 1959, both areas were officially part of Berkeley. In six months the committee of five had pulled this off at a total expense of $195. For those seeking more complete information see the Mason McDuffie archives at the U.C. Bancroft Library and the July 1961 document available at the U.C. Institute of Governmental Studies entitled How Park Hills Moved the County Line: A Self-Study in Citizen Action. \n
        \nOn December 2, 1958, the parcel called Berkeley Woods voted by a count of 118 to 8 to become the sixth addition to the City of Berkeley. On December 16, 1958, the residents of Park Hills voted to become the seventh addition to the City of Berkeley. A special meeting of the Berkeley City Council arranged to bring both parcels into the city by February 1, 1959, the deadline date for third and fourth quarter fiscal year taxes. Thus, by 1959, having expanded seven times, Berkeley would seem to have fulfilled its "manifest destiny" in the extension of its boundaries from bay to ridgeline and from Oakland on the south to the Contra Costa County line on the north and east. \n
        \nThe Berkeley Woods parcel added 70 acres and 102 homes. The Park Hills parcel added 75 acres and 197 homes. The resulting Berkeley acreage was 6,145 acres, over 9 square miles. The City had expanded to twice its 1878 size. The 1878 incorporation papers outlined an area of 3,100 acres. This space was similar to a giant "Y." joining the two separate but adjoining communities of Ocean View and Berkeley, the latter a small but bustling community south and west of the University of California. \n
        \nHike description is courtesy of Paul Grunland\'s notes from the hike he led on April 1, 2000, in conjunction with the with the Berkeley Path Wanderers Association.\n
    </string>
    <string name="hikes_site_name_three">Codornices Creek to Tamalpais Path</string>
    <string name="hikes_site_description_three">
        \nDIRECTIONS\n
        \nBegin at Live Oak Park, Shattuck between Rose and Eunice. Walk upstream along Codornices Creek (east) through the park, crossing and re-crossing on the two bridges. On the south bank, follow the path under the Walnut Street bridge. Continue through the path’s narrow “panhandle” to Oxford Street, either on Berryman Path near the south boundary or via the bridge of the Berkeley Art Center and the dirt path and steep steps leading up to Oxford. On the east side of Oxford Street, detour a short distance south to see the creek, north of Congregation Beth El’s Synagogue. Return and continue east on Berryman Path from Oxford to Spruce. Walk south on Spruce to Glen. Cross Spruce and go east one block on Glen to Arch Street. On Arch Street, walk south to Vine – many interesting old houses, as well as alleyways leading to cottages behind large houses. Walk east one block on Vine. Turn north on Scenic. Where Scenic branches right, uphill, explore the short stub “Spring Street,” named for springs that help feel Codornices Creek. Note the interesting cottages. Return to Scenic and continue northeast, uphill, to Hawthorne Steps. Walk up Hawthorne Steps. At the top of Hawthorne Steps, turn right, south, on Hawthorne Terrace, to Vine Street. At Vine Street, turn east up Vine Street and continue up Vine Lane to Euclid Ave. Walk north on Euclid, past Hawthorne, to the crosswalk at Rose Walk. Walk up Rose Walk. At the top of Rose Walk, turn right, south again, on LeRoy Avenue. Opposite the top of Hawthorne, go east, uphill, on La Loma Steps. At the top of La Loma Steps, turn north on Greenwood Terrace. Continue to Rose Street. (Note that this walk has zig-zagged. From the top of Hawthorne Steps, the direct route would be left up Hawthorne to Euclid, left on Euclid, up Rose Steps to Rose Street just below Greenwood.) From Greenwood, jog left, or west, on Rose to Tamalpais Road. Follow Tamalpais Road north to the top of Tamalpais Path. 13. Walk down Tamalpais Path – a long flight of steps. If the ground is dry, detour on the dirt paths north of the steps to see the spectacular waterfall on the main stem of Codornices Creek. This is private property; don’t abuse the privilege of being allowed to visit. Tamalapis Steps takes you to the north edge of Codornices Park. Stop here for a snack, bathroom break, and to enjoy the Berkeley Rose Garden across Euclid Ave. After your break, walk north on Euclid to Oak Street Path. Take Oak Street Path west past Laurel to Glen Avenue. Walk south on Glen Avenue, crossing Eunice Street, to Summer Street. Walk west on Summer Street to Spruce Street. Cross Spruce Street at the corner. On Spruce Street, jog south to Berryman Path. Follow Berryman Path west back to Live Oak Park. \n
        \nBACKGROUND\n
        \nCostanoans and Rancheros:  Native Americans have inhabited the Bay area since before the Bay itself formed&#8212;about 10,000 years ago, as sea levels rose at the end of the most recent Ice Age. Costanoan, or Ohlone, peoples occupied the Berkeley area when Europeans arrived. The Native American groups probably had various seasonal sites for hunting, gathering, and ceremonies, perhaps with the longest stays and most permanent dwellings near the Bay shore. The mounds of shell and other debris that accumulated at these sites have mostly been blasted away, bulldozed, or paved over, but other artifacts remain – most visibly holes worn in rock by women grinding seeds, at places like Berkeley’s Mortar Rock and the foot of Albany Hill, and pictographs, designs carved in rock, like those at Canyon Trails Park in El Cerrito. \n
        \nUnder the Spanish and later the Mexicans, Berkeley was part of 48,000 acre Rancho San Antonio, which stretched from San Leando Creek to Cerrito Creek (today\’s Alameda/Contra Costa County line. This vast domain was granted to Luis Maria Peralta, a soldier who had arrived in the Bay Area at age 17 with the De Anza expedition. Peralta divided Rancho San Antonio among his sons, with Domingo Peralta receiving the northernmost portion, including what is now Berkeley. Domingo Peralta built his home at today’s Albina Street, next to the creek his family named Codornices, meaning “quail.” \n
        \nFrom several branches in the hills, the creek flowed year-round down to about today\’s Fourth Street. There it probably filtered through a wet grassland to a long north-northwest running salt marsh, drained by a tidal slough. This slough originated at the mouth of Schoolhouse Creek, near today\’s Virginia Street; meandered north between the “mainland” and a small hill that jutted into the Bay, and emptied into the Bay near the northeast corner of this hill. West of the marsh and slough, a spit of low dunes and a sandy crescent of beach curved from about today\’s Delaware Street to the hill, where the shoreline rose in low bluffs. (This hill, later called Fleming Point, was dynamited in 1939 to build Golden Gate Field racetrack. The rubble was pushed north into the Bay to make the racetrack parking lots.) \n
        \nAt the time of the US conquest and the Gold Rush, Berkeley\’s population was 12, probably all ranch employees. Domingo Peraltas sold some of his land&#8212;notably Fleming Point to John Fleming, a butcher who used the near island to fatten cattle. He donated land for the area\’s first school, on the banks of Schoolhouse Creek, near today\’s Virginia Street. But squatters, land speculators, and crooked lawyers led him into a legal morass in which he quickly lost nearly everything else. Domingo Peralta hung on only to his home on Codornices Creek (near today\’s Albina St.) until his death in 1865. \n
        \nA Genteel Failure:  Those who acquired the Peralta land, honestly and not, generally used it for wheat growing or speculation. In the 1860s, Napoleon Bonaparte Byrne bought 1827 acres, from Wildcat Canyon to today\’s Josephine St., and today\’s Cedar to Eunice. A wealthy Southerner seeking health, Byrne came first by steamer from Panama. Returning East, he then crossed the plains in a covered wagon in 1859 with his wife, her mother and sister, four children, and two freed slaves, Berkeley\’s first African American residents. Byrne planned to settle in San Jose, where there was good farmland. But his wife, who loved beauty and nature, persuaded him to stay in Berkeley. The Byrnes built an elaborate Italianate villa on Codornices Creek in 1868, at what is now 1301 Oxford – the Congregation Beth El synagogue. North of the house was a corral, and south an orchard. A drive stretched west to today\’s Walnut Street&#8212;one of the gate supports remains in the park. (The house lasted to become the oldest house in Berkeley, but was torn down in the 1980s after two arson fires.) But beautiful North Berkeley offered poor farming. In the 1870s, Byrne moved to a marshy delta island near Stockton and began selling his house, and the Berkeley land piece by piece, to pay to levee and drain it. Success eluded him again. His wife died of fever. He returned to Berkeley only to fail in the fuel-oil business, apparently because he wouldn\’t dun people to pay their bills. The town eventually gave him a secure living by making him postmaster. \n
        \nBerryman Brings the Commuters:  Byrne\’s house and most of his land were bought by Henry Berryman, an aggressive developer who founded Berkeley Water Works, damming Codornices Creek at today’s Codornices Park to create Berryman Reservoir. He also persuaded the Southern Pacific to extend its steam-train tracks to Berryman Station at Oxford and Rose. (The station is the reason for the curious extra lanes on Shattuck at Long\’s Drugs). He also gave his name to Berryman and Henry Streets. Berkeley was incorporated in 1878 with a boundary just north of today’s Eunice Street, just north of Codornices Creek. Because of the station, this original “north Berkeley” grew faster than the rest of Berkeley during the 1880s. Near Berryman Station were a hotel, various stores, a coal yard, and a volunteer fire company that used the old well at Safeway. North and east of the station, an area of large, prosperous homes grew up, belonging to doctors, business owners, ship captains, and the like. The main meadow of Live Oak Park held a 14 room home belonging to Dr. Michael O\’Toole; the present recreation center area was occupied by a large brown shingle house that was bought by R.S. Penniman, owner of a West Berkeley manufacturing business (and later important in persuading the city to buy the land as a park.) A 20-room tower-decorated Victorian on Vine just above Archwas torn down to accommodate the previous Congregation Beth El. The Victorian at 1431 Arch is the sole survivor of a group of 1880s “view homes” in similar style (it has redwood framing and hand-made nails). In level pockets behind these Arch Street houses were orchards and fields. Today\’s Greenwood Terrace was Captain Thomas\’s orchard and grain fields; the glen bounded by Tamalpais and Shasta was a dairy farm. There also were more modest cottages – those behind 1407 and 1413 Arch date back to as early as 1896. Some belonged to working people; others were summer homes of vacationers from San Francisco, as indicated by the name Summer Street (where houses back onto Codornices).\n
        \nBerkeley\’s Growth Spurt:  Between 1900 and 1910, when Berkeley changed from town to city government, its population soared from 13,000 to over 40,000. There were two main reasons: the Key Route railway began offering a 30 minute commute to San Francisco from the Berkeley Pier in 1903, and the San Francisco Earthquake of 1906 sent people fleeing to what seemed more stable ground. The new houses were still often large, designed by prominent architects and belonging to prominent people, e.g. 2204 Glen (Dempster house, 1908), 1317 Arch (Admiral William Whiting house, 1905), 1320 Arch (Julia Morgan design, 1906), 1324 Arch (Julia Morgan design, 1910), 1325 Arch (Bernard Maybeck design, 1906) 1345 Arch (1909), 1425 Arch (Julia Morgan design, 1910). Development began moving uphill with houses like 1418 Spring (later Scenic, 1909), 1446 Scenic (1908), 1452 Scenic (1908), and 1404 Hawthorne (Julia Morgan design, 1911) (1408 Hawthorne is a later, 1921, Maybeck). Today\’s La Loma Park was quarried for building materials (hence Quarry Rd.); La Loma Park was the generic name for the neighborhood. The Solano Tunnel was built for streetcars between 1908 and 1911. with the excavated dirt used to fill the trestle along today’s Henry Street and what had been a Codornices Creek swimming hole (now School of the Madeleine). This period of rapid growth also saw the continuation of Oxford Street across Codornices Creek to join what had been Pine Street, the construction of Oxford School, and the opening of the Northbrae addition north of Eunice, then outside city limits. The new stretch of Oxford was curved to mollify the owners of the Byrne mansion&#8212;the street cut off most of their front yard and its elegant drive. Neighbors protested, however, when the city proposed extending Berryman east to Spruce to create the street shown on early plat maps. Thus Berryman between Shattuck and Spruce remained a footpath, as it is today.\n
        \nThe Hillside Club Embraces Nature:  Berkeley subdivisions were laid out with curving streets following natural contours as early as the 1870s. This idea was followed in Peralta Park, in what is now the St. Mary\’s High School area, where in the 1880s Caspar Hopkins followed “English landscape gardening” ideas, with curved streets following contours and emphasis on Codornices Creek. The high point, literally and figuratively, was a hotel on the rise now occupied by the high school. But “design with nature” really caught on after 1901, as locals took up the international Arts and Crafts style, shingle style, City Beautiful movement, and Asian influences. Women could not vote, but they could influence. In 1898 a group of women formed the Hillside Club, advocating simple design, harmony with nature, streets that followed contours, and paths for walking and reaching streetcars efficiently. Other influential voices (some in the club) included Joseph Worcester, architect who pursued the local shingle style and “building with nature” (he may have influenced design of his niece’s house at 1307 Bay View Place), landscape painter William Keith (for whom Keith Street is named), Charles Keeler, John Galen Howard (who designed the houses at 1459 and 1486 Greenwood and 1401 Le Roy), Ernest Coxhead (English architect who designed the 1915 school building that is now the BerkeleyRichmond Jewish Community Center), and of course Bernard Maybeck, who designed the simple wooden houses at 1200, 1208, and 1210 Shattuck and 1476 Greenwood. The style they created is called the First Bay Area Tradition. The “Swiss Chalet” apartment building at 1354-64 Scenic was built in 1907 by architect Paul Needham, a somewhat controversial figure: The Hillside Club considered asking Needham and his wife to resign from the Hillside Club because the architect set up portable houses in the Hillside District as a way to let poor people “live in choice localities.” The apartment generated rumblings, too, but its arts-and-crafts style mollified critics.\n
        \nMuch of what the Hillside Club group had pushed for was destroyed in 1923, when fire roared out of Wildcat Canyon and down “Nut Hill,” just north of the University. Some 4000 people in Northeast Berkeley were displaced. Among the homes destroyed was Maybeck\’s on Buena Vista. A stucco house he designed across the street, at 2704, survived. After 1923 stucco was more popular than flammable brown shingle in Berkeley. The Hillside Club, however, did not give up. They raised money to rebuild Rose Walk, and rebuilt their headquarters, in stucco, at the south end of Arch Street. (The cottages along the walk, now owned by the University of California, were designed by Henry Gutterson after the fire. Gutterson also designed 1311 Bay View Place.)\n
        \n“Nature Parks”:  Berkeley was slow to create parks. Although commissions warned that lack of recreation was leading to delinquency, voters refused to approve funds. There were a few playgrounds, but the city\’s first “nature park,” planned to preserve greenery and open space, was Live Oak Park, purchased in 1914 from the O\’Toole and Penniman families. The lush creek canyon made a pleasant contrast to the bare, treeless hills&#8212;and anyone could easily reach the area with 6 cent carfare. One of the first improvements was the present Walnut Street Bridge, designed in 1915. In 1916 the North Branch of the Berkeley Public Library moved to the old Penniman house, which became the park clubhouse. (It burned in 1951; the huge wisteria west of the present Recreation Center is a remnant.) Live Oak Park\’s large stone fireplace beside the creek was completed in 1917. The first such gathering place in the city, it was a vital part of community life in those days before radio, television, or widespread individual ownership of automobiles. Other parks followed: Codornices Park was leased from the water company as a playground in 1915. John Hinkel gave Hinkel Park and its clubhouse to the city in 1919 – his house and a former hunting lodge south of the park remain. The city built large stone fireplaces in both parks, testifying to the popularity of such gathering places. Grotto, Mortar, and Indian Rock Parks were acquired from Northbrae’s developers in 1920, when Berkeley annexed the area. But Live Oak remained Berkeley\’s most heavily used park. The large fireplace hosted more than 10,000 people and 300 gatherings a year.\n
        \nA Note on Schoolhouse Creek:  The walk crosses back and forth between drainages of the Middle and South Forks of Codornices Creek and Schoolhouse Creek&#8212;a small, all but forgotten creek between Strawberry and Codornices. Its rises from ephemeral feeder streams and swales that drained the hills from just south of Berryman Reservoir to the south part of the fenced-off Lawrence Berkeley Lab property. These feeders remain visible only here and there, as in the yard just north of the base of Vine Steps, and at the end of present-day Spring Street (named for springs). A slight rise and fall as you walk north on streets like Oxford shows the natural levees formed by floods of Codornices and Schoolhouse. Lower down, the creek\’s former canyon is deeper, larger, and still obvious in dips and curves in the area of Jayne Street. The creek emerges in a few yards in the general area of Cedar-Rose Park and North Berkeley BART. The massive culvert built by the Santa Fe Railway northwest of North Berkeley BART also shows the creek’s course. Schoolhouse was mostly straightened and culverted in the 19th and very early 20th Centuries. Its lower course originally carried it into a willow grove at the head of the north-running tidal slough that also received the waters of Codornices Creek. But this segment was commandeered to carry raw sewage – the very large pipe emerging at the creek mouth, just north of Virginia Extension in what is now the Eastshore State Park, was built to carry both creek and sewer flows. The hope is to someday “daylight” the creek here, creating a new channel outlet and a small salt marsh.\n
        \nHike description is courtesy of the Berkeley Path Wanderers Association website.\n
    </string>

    <string name="homes_site_name_one">White / Lange House</string>
    <string name="homes_site_description_one">1163 Euclid Ave, Berkeley, CA 94708\n
        \nBay Area architect John White, brother-in-law of architect Bernard Maybeck, designed this home as his own residence in 1911. The brown-shingled home features a Craftsman style and a rustic exterior with a more formal interior, which is typical of White’s style.\n
        \nDocumentary photographer Dorothea Lange lived and worked in this house with her husband, UC economics professor Paul Taylor, for the last 25 years of her life, from 1940 to 1965.\n
        </string>
    <string name="homes_site_name_two">Rose Walk Cottage</string>
    <string name="homes_site_description_two">
        \nNonfiction writer Michael Lewis, author of The Big Short, Moneyball, Liar’s Poker, and The Blind Side, and wife Tabitha Soren, fine art photographer and former MTV journalist, have lived along the Rose Walk with their children since 1999.\n
        </string>
    <string name="homes_site_name_three">Pratt-Thomas House</string>
    <string name="homes_site_description_three">800 Shattuck Ave, Berkeley, CA 94707\n
        \nThe Pratt-Thomas House commands its site as a result of its massive buttresses and parapet gables and by the vertical linking of the large living room and second story windows via decorative woodwork. Characteristically, Thomas\'s elaborate muntins blend windows of otherwise radically different sizes and shapes into an overall design. The entry on the Shattuck Avenue side is sheltered by a massive cantilevered stucco box whose enormous window floods the interior stairway and entry hall with light. While he lived in the house, Thomas himself is said to have taken advantage of this lovely window by making the upstairs landing large enough to accommodate his drafting table. The floor plan is one of two often used by Thomas: the living room is to one side of the entry; the kitchen is to the other; and the dining room is just on the other side of the entry\’s interior wall. Few changes have been made in the original design. The door from the pantry-dining nook has been widened slightly, and a side sun porch has been enclosed by door and window. Fir cabinets in the pantry were returned to their natural finish by the present owners. Fixtures throughout the house are the original gas outlets electrified. Fir was used for ornamental trim in this home: note the bench alcove in the entry and the small candle alcove at the top of the stairs, two charming echoes of the Craftsman tradition. Wood in a four-square decorative motif directs the eye to the ceiling in both the living and dining rooms. This Thomas signature is repeated in plaster and tile on the living room and master bedroom fireplaces. Both the living room and master bedroom feature cozy fireplace inglenooks, a design repeated in larger Thomas houses.
        The large rectangular windows of the living room and the curving dining room bay are additional features that foster the illusion of a much grander scale than the actual size of the house would otherwise suggest.\n
        \nCommentary by Susan Fisher.\n
        </string>
    <string name="homes_site_name_four">The Hume Cloister</string>
    <string name="homes_site_description_four">2900 Buena Vista Way, Berkeley, CA 94708\n
        \nBuilt by John Hudson Thomas in 1929. This home features an inner courtyard built around elements of a cloister imported from France. Original owner Samual James Hume was the head of Berkeley\'s Greek Theater Department, and his wife worked in the field of psychiatry. The estate features Gothic and Medieval design elements, such as Florentine lamps, pointed barrel vaults, and the dining room\’s cast iron chandelier.\n
        </string>

</resources>
